Good morning friends.  How are you guys?
So bye guys welcome everyone.  So today we are going to talk
about the insurance sector.  Insurance sector means we will
talk about life insurance sector.  We will
talk about general insurance and health
insurance.  Which stocks are good
and how should one invest there
?  What should be the strategy and what does the
future look like?  Because if you see, there has been a
decent return for some time now.  Let me do one
thing, I will show you the screener.
So if we talk about what kind
of results have been there so far, like this
insurance company, let me tell you what the
returns have been like.  Look at the last 3 years
return of Life Insurance LIC is 6-7%.
Only HBI accounts for 16%.  HDFC has 10.   The
determinant of L is 12.  Max's is good.
But overall the
life insurance company does not give such great returns.  Almost No has
sometimes given returns below the market.
So the insurance company has not performed that way
and I am
talking specifically about life insurance.
If you look at life insurance, the overall
returns are decent.  Now if we
look at the returns of general insurance, it
is comparatively good.  If you see, ICICI
is 16.  General's is 30%.  So New India
is 11.  So I am seeing decent returns there.
Of course we have to see company
to company.  Now we will talk about
what it seems from here because this year has
not been good for general insurance in terms of
one year's returns and if we
talk about life insurance also, it
is good there.  If we look at HBI, HDFC is bigger by 41% and HDFC by 22%.
Max is older than 52.  Now we have to see
which insurance company will grow from here
and in which one we should invest.
This is a long-term trend.  This
is a mega trend and if you always stay in the mega trend for a
long time then you can
get good returns.  So insurance
penetration is very low in India.  It will
grow in the future but not all companies will grow.
Some companies will grow.  So we will
see how to evulate.  Before going further, guys,
whatever is being said here is
only for your information.  There are
no recommendations here.  From your end, we
give recommendations in our service which
you
can see by going to www.c.in and
you can see our packages.  And here guys
please do your reset and invest.
Ok?  And if you have any question,
please post it in the comment box.  Hope you can hear my voice then
just type yes in the
chat box.  If you have any question, please
write it down.  I will do answer those questions.
So let's talk about insurance companies.
So look at the insurance company, there
is a little technical expectation here that it is
not like a normal manufacturing company or service industry.
When you evaluate it, the way you
check it, you will have to look at it from a slightly different angle.  It is
not that you can
normally look at sales and profitability.
Some of their metrics or
parameters are different.  So this
session will also be a bit educational in nature.
Off course I will talk about the company
but it is important to explain to you.
So this is the thing.  Ok?  So you please do that a little bit.
But it will be a very very
important video for you.  So please watch till the end.
So as I said
about the insurance company, the
metrics that you have to look at in the insurance company are
decided one by one.  Let us see.
First, let's see how these guys have
increased sales and profitability
over the years.  So if we talk about
how the sales and profitability have
increased in the last 3 years, then look at the increase in life
insurance from just 7% to 12% and
11% for SBI, that is, their revenue jump
overall is not that significant.  And
of course the profitability of LIC has also increased.
But what has happened to him?  Getting a DD rating.
Its PE ratio is decreasing.
And that is a problem.
HBI and HDFCO have slightly decent returns in profitability and ICICI Pro has
slightly decent returns in Pru.  So here if
we talk about ICICI's lumber or something like that, then even in that there is
a
decent return but there is a jump in sales.
Even I think Go Digit's is pretty good.
Go Digit has become very famous.  Style accounts
for 14%.  But profitability growth is
growing comparatively well.  So let me
first share the important points that
you have to keep in mind.
When you look at a life insurance company,
these are the important parameters that
you should keep in mind. Let's
discuss them one by one.  So first we come to the
value of new business.  For this I am not
saying that you will be
better off with Tjori Finance than Skinner.  Because
what happens in Tijori Finance is that
all these parameters are given well in it.
Normally sales profitability would be
given in the screener.  So I think it is better to use Tijori Finance when you
evaluate insurance companies.
So VNB now
what is VNB margin?  Look, I will have to
explain each concept one by one because the concepts of health,
sorry life health and general
insurance are all slightly
different.  So I will have to explain each concept one by one.
So please bear it a little.
But listen quietly and very carefully.
If you really want to invest in an insurance company, then
we also
look at all these things when our
clients invest, when we invest,
I and my research team
look at all these parameters.  By the way, as I
said, you can go and check our website
www.cp.in
and you will see that there is membership here and you
can see that.  Ok?  So you can definitely avail it.
And by the way, if you guys do
n't follow me on YouTube, please do.
How many people follow me there
on YouTube, then just save yes in
the chat box, I upload a lot of videos
today like this is about trend, about cements,
in this direction I talk about a lot of stocks,
these are some TV videos
which are NDTV or Money or I
come regularly on CBS, so there are some videos of that too,
you can watch them, okay then definitely watch it, it will be very very
useful to you
talking about no life insurance, so
VNB as I said value of
new business.  So what is the value of new business,
look
what happens in an insurance company?  Like the new customers who
come.  Ok?  And those customers come and
how much margin do you get in that?  That means, for the
next 2 years, consider that you are
running a coaching class.  Ok?  So the
fee for one person is ₹10,000.  Ok?
But your Rs 10,000 is not real profit, right?
You add your own money to that and don't
take out the support cost.  Infrastructure
cost, that refund also happens sometimes and suppose
you earned ₹2500 from that person, okay, then
that ₹500 is the profit value, that is the
value of new business, okay, so just like now, suppose an
insurance company does new business,
suppose it does new business of ₹1 and from that it
also earns ₹24, okay, so that
₹24 is the value of new business, okay, and
how it is growing is very
important.  So as I have already told you
that if the margin of value of new business is
between 24 to 28% then
that is a good parameter
for the company.  Now if you look here as I said,
you can get this value of new business from here in Tichori Finance,
look in this I have already
selected the companies HDFC SBI ICICI Pro, you
will say Tapan what about
LIC, look I can add life insurance also
but its value
is so big that it comes a little higher.
Like, if I look at the embedded value, then
see where the life insurance company is and all the
other companies because this company is
10 times bigger than all the other companies, so
I will keep some parameters and will
not keep some parameters, like if you look at the value of new
business, if you see,
HBI L has 27% which is very good,
its margin is 24%, HDFC has 24%, ICIC has 24% and LIC has
only 16%.  That means LIC's expense i.e.
its margin which is coming from new business is
comparatively very low compared to other
players.  So that's something you have to
look at.  The more it is, the better.
Ok?  Secondly, one more
point that I told us is APE growth.
What is APE growth?  Annualized
Premium Equivalent.  Ok?  That is, the
premium that you charge means a customer
comes to you and
pays the premium for insurance.  It can also be a single premium.
This is one time payment and
regular premium i.e. he should pay it every year.
That is, sometimes what happens is that someone
says, okay take this premium of Rs 5 lakh and
give me a policy for 20 years.  There is one who makes a one-
time payment and there is one
who pays the premium year after year.  So
if you calculate its total premium year by year, then you have to
discount it from the equity cost and
bring it to the current value.  But that
growth, the growth in premium is
called APE growth.  And that is
very important, that is, indirectly when you make
sales, how much value you get, that is it.  If
APA growth happens indirectly
for LIC then it will be something between 12 to
18% for you, so that is good.  Ok
?  Look, as I said, the
parameters in every insurance company are different.  The
name is different.  So just like there are
cells in ours, there is APE here.
OK Got It?  So what is an APE
?  Annualized Premium Equivalent.  Ok guys I know this is a
bit technical but
stay with me guys.  That's why
I'm giving you back the Matrix already.
You should keep these important metrics
in mind.
Ok?  Are You With Me Guys?  Then just w
for you vs you in the chat.  W for VU
in the chat box.  You have to have some patience
in this.  Ok?  And one that I'm talking about is the
persistent ratio.
Persistency Ratio.  Now what is that?
Look, you understand.  Like in SIP.
You have done an SIP of ₹1000.  Ok?  So if you have done an
SIP of ₹1000 then you keep renewing it, that
is, it gets debited every month.
Well, the premium which is
maybe quarterly, half yearly and yearly,
basically what happens to you is that it gets debited.
So how much debit is happening, that is,
no one is breaking it in between,
like we break it in SIP, similarly no
one is breaking it in insurance, so that is the
persistence ratio,
simple age, that is, right now it is 13th and 60th.
So in this I tell
you the value of new business.  Ok
?  And secondly, as I said,
persistence ratio.  Here it is.  See, there are two
types of ratios.  One is 13 month
ratio and the other is 16 first month ratio.
What is the 13-month ratio, who is paying for the 13 months
?  Ok?  It is
called 13 Month Persistent Ratio and it
increases to 60 months, that is, who is doing this for 5 years,
okay so 13 months and 61 months, you will
get it from here, so see the ratio of 13 months will
always be on a higher side, see this 85%
84% 82%, you all are seeing it here, okay, if
I have added LIC or not, the
system is
yes, then you can also see LIC,
okay.  So LIC's is also almost 68.  So it is
decreasing in LIC.  Everything else is getting more done.
And if we take 61 months
then it will be a little less comparatively than 13 months
because as the term gets longer
some people do not renew it.
Ok?  If he is 61 months old then the
ratio in him is less.  This is important to see.
Whatever the higher rate, for example, if you look at HDFC Life here, it is
62%, so it is very good.  That means
people are continuing that policy.  Got it?
So that is what you have to keep on the person
ratio.  Now you will tell me how much heat should there be
?  So 60 means what I am saying is that if
it is above 60% in 5 years then it is
good for the company.  clear?
Now comes the embedded value.  ROB means
Return on Embedded Value.  First of all,
what is embedded value?  See
what happened to the embedded value?  Basically your net
worth is like the net worth of a company
plus the future profit value, that is,
see, insurance is a different type of business, on
top of your current net worth, the
profit you will earn in the future, the
premium you will collect and after deducting the cost,
how much is left for you, that is the embedded
value.  So net worth plus future profit
value.  Now what the return on embedded value is,
it basically looks at
how it's growing.  Ok.  So
if you look at the ROE, almost if
its net worth is increasing by more than 13% every year, that is,
embedded value net worth plus future
profit, then that is a good signal.  So
if it is growing around 13% then it
is better.  Now look at the embedded value here,
see how much is the life insurance
?
One is 813230
crores while SBI's is 76000.  HDFC L has ₹
59,000.  That means
LIC has such a huge embedded value, which means it is a
good company.  It's not like that.  How much
is the growth?  What is the growth every year?  The problem right now is
that it is not mentioned here
how much the growth is.  You will get growth from ROE.  If it is
more than 13% then it
is very good for the company.  Got It Guys?  Ok?
You can put any question in the chat box.
I know it is a bit technical but embedded
value is also a kind of net
worth for the insurance company.   The
second one is the solvency ratio.  Now
what is solvency ratio?  Solvency
ratio means whether they have enough money
if claims come.  Ok.  So if we
see
how, for example, first let
me understand and you understand what is solvency ratio
?  Solvency ratio is the same that brother,
if there is enough capital, if there is some flood or
Corona or Corona comes and there are many
deaths in it, then because of that you will have to make a lot of
payment.  So do they have
enough money to pay that or not?
So the more hires there are, the
better it will be for the company.  So what should the solvency ratio be
?  1.5 times what IRDA is saying it should be.
Ok?  That means
you should have 1.5 times the amount claimed.  If it is
at least 1.8 times then it
is a comfortable position.  clear?  So your assets should be minimum
1.5 times more than your liabilities
so that you can make that payment.
clear?  So that is a solvency ratio
because sometimes what happens is that if you do
n't have a solvency ratio, if you do
n't have solvency, then there is a problem.  Like let me tell you one thing, there is
no direct example.  But
when the Lemon Brothers
crisis happened, I forgot the name of the AI.
AIG I forgot the name.  Anyone
Can Tell Me Remember Just I Have Yes in the
Chago.  At that time some US insurance
companies had defaulted.  Why?  Because the
claim he had to pay was
more than his net worth.  If you remember just yes in I do
n't know I wanted AI or which one it was
I don't remember exactly.
But because of that the insurance
company defaulted there.  So solvency ratio
plays a very very big role.  So these are some
points to keep in mind when you
look at a life insurance company.  So
as I told the life insurance company,
your VNB margin should be
good, this value of no, this
margin should be good.  So how much should that be
?  24 to 28% then annual premium
growth equivalent growth should be 12 to
18%.  Persistence
Ratio means this is the embedded value of 16 months
and 13 months, that of 60 months
is above 60%, in that the return on
embedded value is more than 13%, so that is a
good embedded value, that is, this is
yours and if the solvency ratio is 1.8 times, then
that company will be considered good,
yes it was AIG, right, okay, so keep it
in white when you are talking about
insurance companies till now it is clear guys, then just
type C for clear in the chat
box.  I have already
put that matrix in the comment box.  Okay, now we will
take another one, which one will we take?
Take health insurance.  Let's get health insurance now.  So,
you know that health insurance had a
huge impact during the Corona period.  So, if
you look at what is happening because of that,
then all these companies had a big
problem.  But let's see what happens now.
So let us see
what are the ratios in health insurance that
you need to keep in mind.  I will give it to you.
So we will talk to you more about that in the end.
Which company
is good and which one should I invest in
?  So we also want to
talk a little futuristic about that.  Ok?  You got this
point guys.  You got the points, then just have
yes in the chat box, Y for yes in
the chat box,
so the first thing you have to see in health insurance is the
claim ratio, brother, how is the
claim ratio, how is the claim
ratio coming, and what is a claim or nothing,
if you suffer any loss
and you have taken insurance, then you make a
claim, okay, so that is the
claim ratio in simple terms, now the claim ratio
also has a ratio, you have to keep that
in mind, how have
you done for the company, like I have
taken a premium of ₹100.  Ok?  A premium of ₹100 has
come and against that a claim of ₹70 has
come.  So that is called 70% claim ratio.
The lower the claim ratio, the
more profit you make.  Ok?  And
if the claim ratio is between 65 to 75 percent then it is
good for the company.
Why?  Because in 2025 they will have some other
expenses.  Ok?  So if other
expenses are high and the claim ratio is also
high then it will result in loss.  Now
you see all this, these things which I am talking about will be available in the
safe.  If you do not get it here then
you will have to look at the annual report.
Quarterly Result or IRDA Report,
from there you can get all these details.
But the claim ratio should be somewhere between 65 to 75%.  The
second one comes is combined
ratio.  What is combined ratio?
Combined ratio means your claim ratio
plus as I said,
you will have some expenses also.  Ok?  So like
here it is, if you see here then the combined
ratio comes.  So look at the combined ratio,
for example, New India's is 139.
General Insurance is 109.  ici's is 105.
Star Health has 103.  So the combined
ratio means claim ratio plus
expenses.  Now you will get the question that if the
premium is 109% then the company will incur loss.
Just y for years correct.  You might be thinking
that if your combined
ratio, your
claim plus expenses, is more than 100%, then your
expenses are more than your earnings.  Correct but there
is a twist in it.  What is a twist?  Look, it is the
combined ratio, if it is below 100% then it is
good.  Now you will say that there is loss even in 100,
right?  No.  Look what happens to you is that you
get the premium today.  Like you
received the premium but when the claim came, it came
two years later, one year later, sometimes you did
not receive the claim at all.  The claim did
not come for years.  Like, many times it happens that
you have taken health insurance but you are
not making any claim.  I have been paying for health insurance for the last 15 years
but the
claims are not coming.  I have never been hospitalized yet.
So in the meantime, will your money
that you have given to the insurance remain
lying there?  No.  It will be invested somewhere.
Some will invest in FD, some
in government bonds, some
in RBI bonds.  So you will
get interest from there.  So the interest you get is
called float.
So understand that it is a float.  So the
interest they get from that plus your premium,
they do not face much problem because
you are getting 30-40% in two-three years and have already
earned 30-40% in four years.  Even if it goes to
110 or 120 again, you will still earn that.
Got it then just have G for got it.  What
I am trying to convey is that even if
your expense ratio and
combined ratio is big, why are you
not going into loss because you
got interest, right, for example, if you had invested
₹100, your
combined ratio would have been ₹1, but what did that person do, if he paid
premium somewhere, then understand from there that he
earned 110, 120, 10 in 2 years, so if there is
100 combined ratio in front of 110, then
he will still earn 10, yes Shiv Nandini, Shailendra,
Satish got it?  So, this is the thing.
Float has a great advantage in insurance companies.  Like let
me tell you, let's talk about Vern
Buffett.  Vern Buffett also has an insurance company.
Correct.  So what is BSE Hathaway?  That
is an insurance company.  So whatever
premium they get becomes their fund in a way
and they invest it somewhere.
So they earn from there.  Then when it
comes in 2 years, 3 years, 5 years or anytime, they
pay it and the interest they
get in between after deducting the expenses is their
profit.  So that is what they are getting the
benefit out of this.
We will also talk about Sushant which is the best insurance.  Please
wait a little.  I am
explaining the concept to you a little.  So this
combined ratio is very different to
understand.  Ok?  So this is one thing you have to keep
in mind.  Now the second point which I
told you.  So if the combined ratio
is below 100% then it is good.  The second is
GWP growth.  Now what is that?  GW means P
i.e. Gross Return Premium Growth.  That means
how much is your premium growing?
It is as simple as that, if that premium growth is between 15 to 25%, that is,
how much are the sales increasing, if it happens like this, then
how much are the sales increasing, if it is growing between 15 to 20%, then it is
very good, that
is a good thing and one point which I have given you
in the matrix is ​​renewal
ratio, that is, if someone has
taken health insurance from you, then when does he renew it or
not, that is, it is the same thing which I
told you about persistency ratio,
here renewal ratio, like what I said,
life insurance has different parameters, that is, the
names of the parameters are different for health.
But in
simple terms, if your renewal ratio is 85%, then it
is good in a way.  Ok?
The second is the expense ratio.
What is expense ratio, brother, other than claim
ratio.  So in the combined ratio, I
told you that your total
claim ratio is claim plus expense.
What happened in The Expanse?  Your commissions are there
, your marketing is there, your operational
costs are there.  That is called expense
ratio.  Your expense ratio should be below 25 to 30%.
So if the claim ratio is 70%
and expense ratio is 30% then your
total combined ratio is 100 and you are
taking 100 premium but
you are earning the interest on it,
keep this in mind that it never goes exactly like this
but I am saying this just to draw your attention, so
now
you should look at this thing in this way, here also you should
look at this risk rate, this float as I
said, what is this float, what is float?   The
float is that interest.
Ok?  What I told you is that you
earn extra.  So this is how you have to keep it in
mind.  Ok?  Of course
you can go deeper into this.  I don't have much time right now
but I am telling you in general.   Let me bring you
back these health insurance
metrics that you need to keep in mind.
Guys, are you getting value or
not?  Just a V for value.
You will be learning something new.  I think you may have never
seen or heard anything like this.
So this thing
is difficult to understand because the insurance company.  I tell
you one of a very very difficult sector
to value it to understand it.  Because in reason,
these are not in simple terms.
It contains NT.  It has
ULIP.  Actually you have heard about this
which is the number one profession.  Someone actually
becomes a just time wife if you have heard so that
he can charge a lot.  Actually, what
they do is that this
valuation which we are talking about right now does
complete forecasting
that brother, this much should be kept, this much premium should be
charged, in this it works on the probability
that this much claim can come in future.  It
is a very tough course to crack.  If you can do that, you
get very good money.  If your
children have to do it then make it an actual
because the insurance business is never going to die.
Ok?  But he should
not be good at maths.  That
probability is this or that, but yes it is a very
wonderful profession.  If very few people
get that license.  Very few people
get it and they decide all this, like if you are
bringing a new insurance product
then how much premium should be charged,
then how much claim can come, everything related to this, okay so
this was health insurance, now let's
talk a little about general insurance,
okay so there are some pointers for general insurance as well
which I want to give you here, let me give you
1 minute right now so that you know,
just a minute,
so in general insurance like you have vehicle
insurance, you have cyber insurance
or you can say that there are
many other things which you normally
insure, other than health and
life, this is what
you have got, then you just have by for years, okay so
this is general insurance, in this also
some points which you already know, I am
just repeating them to you but
you have to keep these pointers in mind.
So what is the first one?  Combined ratio.
Ok?  What happened to the combined ratio?  As I
already told you that your claim
ratio plus expense ratio is
called combined ratio.  So do
we know how much to keep in it?  6 95 to 7
100% so what can they earn from float.
Ok?  The second is the loss ratio.
What is the loss ratio?  That means the same thing happened with the claim
ratio.  This is called loss ratio.  That too, if
a vehicle meets with an accident and there is a
loss, then a claim is made.  So if
your claim ratio is almost below 70% then
it is good because you
already have an expense ratio which
you have to pay.
Ok?  So that is the loss ratio.  The second is
GDPI ratio i.e. Gross Direct
Premium Income.
In short, have you seen the sales of each one of them, the
name is different.  Like we
say in general insurance that the
vehicle insurance you take or the travel
insurance you take and all that.  So the
premium that comes to you, okay?
You call that premium this one.
A what did I say?  Sales is sales growth,
otherwise it is called premium growth.
So you will know that from GDPI growth.
If that 10 to 15% is
for general insurance then it is good.
Third came Cat.  Now they will say this is Cat's.
No cat, this is not a cat.  Cat
losses means catastrophe losses means flood has come.
The building burned down.  There was a cyber attack.
Ok?  Or you said yes, like for example, what
happened recently in Indigo, 2000 flights got cancelled.
Now whoever has taken travel insurance must have
earned a lot.  Agri and Not
Dangerous is before Agri's brother flight got
cancelled.  Brother, give me my money, okay, this is it, a
big loss occurs like this.  The
company will suffer losses simultaneously.  Now 2000 together,
now not everyone might have taken life, sorry,
travel insurance, but whoever might have taken it, it is
beneficial for them, if there is a flood then
no, at the end of the day there is a problem there too, it is
called cattle, that is, flood,
cyclone, heavy rainfall, so
if you have a loss then it is good because
if it increases, like this Covid which happened,
no one predicted it, so its
loss is big.  Or when the Titanic sank, the
companies that had taken insurance for it also sank.
Such a huge loss had occurred.  So that is
catastrophic loss and the fifth is your
investment yield i.e. the premium that
you take, that is basically
float.  Ok?  The name is different.  So if you
invest the premium you are getting somewhere else, you get
interest on it.  That is called
investment year.  That too should be stable.
If he is your stable then it is good.
So basically as I said, this is the combined
ratio, then the loss ratio, GDPI ratio
and I have given you all those metrics.  I do
one thing and give all three together.
So you can copy it.
Okay now let us talk company wise till now it is
clear guys.  Okay clear than just have
C for clear.  Okay you are getting knowledge and
not then just have K for knowledge in the chat
box.  Okay for knowledge because look, this, I know,
this half an hour might have seemed very
technical to you.  But it
is very important to understand this.  Whenever you see any insurance
company.  How do you feel when we talk now
?  Which companies
will run now?  Life will go on, general will go on, health will
go on.  What kind of companies will survive now?  So
here you should see that overall, there are some
government rules or all this,
we should also discuss that
here because it has an impact.  For example,
what
happened in the recent deregulation of GST was that the GST that was being levied on the premium was
removed from your life insurance, health insurance,
but it is not levied on general insurance.
Vehicle loan and GST on it are still
applicable.  So what has happened because of that is that the
life insurance companies or health companies have to
take ITC.  Okay, you want to take tax credit,
inward tax credit is not available in
GST.  So the companies there will suffer a
little loss for one or two quarters.  It will
stabilize later.  It came into effect from September 22.
But there are some riders in this also like
in health insurance, group
insurance and all that, GST is still applicable there, in
some places it has been
removed at individual level but it is still there at that level, so
you have to keep this thing in mind
that if you say that there will be
no credit from IT then will the companies suffer a
big loss due to this, but no, the companies will
adjust their rates accordingly and plus
somewhere they can increase the premium.
Ok?  Now that 18% GST has been removed, it does
not mean that your premium has reduced to
less than 18%.  No, by increasing the rates by 2-3%, they will
somehow
set off the loss they are incurring and we have
seen this in health insurance.  But the
overall benefit of this will be that in future the
growth of insurance can be good
because if your overall premium comes down
then it will benefit everyone in that way.
Secondly, you know that the new
tax regime in ETC is as per income tax,
in the new tax regime the benefit of ETC has been
removed from life and health and if the new
regime remains in future then that too will have a little impact
but I think that too will be set off.
Look, this is all a policy trick.  There is
some impact due to changes in the policy.
But not so much that the
company will start incurring losses or there will be no demand for the company.  There
is demand going forward.  We
are still under-benefited.  Even now, if I am not wrong,
8 to 9% of the population has
taken life insurance or health
insurance, then friend, four or five people must have taken it.
Whereas if you look at the world over, it
is very high.  Like I was in Dubai, so it was
compulsory in Dubai.  It is compulsory in the US also.
There is 98% to
100% insurance.  We don't have it here
because the public is so large, so it does make a
difference, but it is very under-
penetrated.  So there is growth going forward.
But it is not necessary that everyone will grow.
Ok?  So whatever ITC or
GST comes from this premium
is beneficial, even the exemption in long term income tax which has been
removed does not have such a big
impact and if you see, life
insurance and all that is growing slowly right now.
Health insurance is growing rapidly.  The
speed of health insurance
is higher compared to life insurance.  Because
after Covid, suddenly people felt that they would have to
take this.  There is no doubt in that
because the death that has occurred is correct but there was
no benefit for health insurance during the time of Covid but those Indians
who took it got the benefit, so if
you see now, the demand for health insurance has
increased a lot and because of that the
hospitals are also getting benefit,
if you have taken health insurance then
you can get knee replacement done or eye
replacement or eye operation done, whatever it is, then
they are getting benefit.  Ok.  So there will be
demand for both to a large extent.  General
insurance vehicles are increasing.
Now if you look at it,
how were the automobile sales of this type this time?  It has been tremendous.
Ok?  So your insurance has become compulsory with all vehicles.  It has
become mandatory.  So the more vehicles there are, the
higher the insurance.  Nowadays,
people have started taking travel insurance for fire at home also.
Because the kind of
situation that Indigo has faced, if something happens in future, then it will face a
geopolitical crisis somewhere
and some flights get cancelled, hotels get
cancelled, whatever it is, that is also a
benefit, so in this way, there will be a
lot of penetration of insurance in India, you
will ask Tapan, what do you think, will life increase or
general increase, health increase, let me
ask you, what according to you will increase, write L for
life, write H for health, write G for general.
Type in the chat box.  Let me
ask you.  According to you, will L increase, H
increase or will general insurance increase more?   Your
life will increase.  Growth, growth, I'm talking.
Growth I
think mostly everyone got it right.  90% of all
people have said health and general
insurance and you are right.  Health and
general insurance should increase a lot
because nowadays health insurance is a
huge medical expense, look at it.
Plus their premium is
reasonable.  Ok?  And
any person can take part in it.  Plus general
insurance has also become compulsory these days, right?
Compulsory.  That means if you buy a vehicle then you have to buy it.
Life is not compulsory.  Health is
not compulsory.  But general is compulsory.  If you
buy a vehicle, you have to take insurance by
default.  Without that, some memo will come to
your house.  So even I do believe that you guys are
right.  I also feel that general
insurance and health insurance will cost more.
If you look at the returns of all the
stocks, then which one has
given higher returns, if you look at the last year,
now life is a little higher since last one year but over
the years general insurance and health
insurance has given a good return
comparatively, in which whether I talk about ICICI or LBA
or New India Insurance and all that,
but life is such a thing which is
giving consistent returns, health and
general are like this, life is a little like this, it is
very consistent.  So if you
say 1315% then life is
continuously doing well in that.  Take SBI
, take HDFC.  But did
not give excellent results.  A Max Finance has
given good results.  But Max Finance also
pretty much covers everything else in there.
That's why sleep insurance should be
in your portfolio.  Again, what I am
saying again, guys, whatever I am
discussing is for your knowledge,
as I told you earlier, I am
telling you again that the recommendations we
give are there on our website.
Ok?  And accordingly, please do your
own research before investing.   Don't do it because
I say so.  As simple as that.
Ok?  So I feel like
General and Health will grow.  Life
performed well.  So he will continue doing it.  Currently there are only a few
insurance companies.  In life
you know there is HDFC, ICIC, SBI, Max.
But all these three companies SBI is doing a little
better.  Why is SBI doing well
?  Because I have noted one thing in life insurance
that the one whose bank
insurance is good is good.
What happens with bank insurance is that the person who is
selling the policy from the bank, his
performance is normally better than his bank,
hence SBI is very good.  SBI is far ahead
because they have more branches.  OK
and the network is more.  So you know that SBI and HDFC are
also performing well.
ICICI LMD has performed very well in general insurance from ICICI.  I
think it is one of the
best comparatively.  He has just come to Niva BP.
Then a Go D disease has come.  But
in all this, the valuation is still a bit tough.
So please keep that in mind.
Another one in health insurance is Star
Health.  But somehow it is not able to
perform.  Yes, he has been very famous.
Rakesh Jhunjhunwala's own investment.
But it did not give the kind of result that you are
thinking about. What is the problem in health insurance,
that a big epidemic comes
like Corona has come and every
five, six, ten years, such a calamity
or medical emergency
comes due to which the profit
reduces a little.  But this does not happen in general insurance.
I have seen a steady growth in general insurance over the time,
so you should keep that in mind, it is
important to invest in other insurances because other
companies are good for steady growth, but the only thing is that if
you invest keeping in mind the pointers that I have given you, I think it will be
very good, we
also see this whenever I and my system, they are also concerned
chartered accountants and
they are SEBI registered sir, so whenever we
see it, we see it very carefully
because firstly the business is tough to evaluate.
I am telling the truth, it is tough for me too.
Insurance: I made you
memorize so many terminologies today. Normally, I don't tell you
so much in these sessions that we conduct.
Why do I have to tell
?  Because this business is different and to a large
extent it depends on market dynamics, that is, if some
calamity comes or this or that happens, a
lot depends on that too.  So it is a bit tough
but they are consistent in this, but the
policy changes also have a significant impact on it.
Like suddenly something
comes in the budget regarding life insurance
or GST, then it
depends a lot on the changes in the policy
and so you have to keep that thing in mind.
Ok?  So let's keep it up to here, Guys.
So how did you like this session?  Did you get the knowledge
or not?  Yes What You Learned Today?
Investment in market securities is
subject to market risk. Read all the
documents carefully before investing.